Finding Aid for Stephen Hopkins Spurr Papers 1940-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stephen Hopkins Spurr Papers 1940-1971, 1952-1968
Spurr, Stephen Hopkins.
4 linear feet
Professor of forestry, dean of the School of Natural Resources, University vice-president and dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies of University of Michigan; president of University of Texas. Files concern his work with the Organization for Tropical Studies, the Ramparts Canyon Dam Project in Alaska, and other professional work.
8677 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Prof. Spurr (donor 4496 ) in four accessions in 1968 and 1971.
The collection is open for research.
Stephen Hopkins Spurr was a professor of forestry at the University of Michigan and other institutions, who spent a major part of his career at Michigan and the University of Texas as a university administrator.
Spurr was born in 1918 and received his undergraduate degree from the University of Florida. After earning a graduate degree from the Yale forestry school in 1940, he worked at the Harvard Forest and the University of Minnesota before becoming professor of silviculture at the University of Michigan in 1952. While at Michigan Spurr took on administrative responsibilities, becoming dean of the School of Natural Resources in 1962, dean of the Graduate School in 1964, and vice president and dean of graduate studies in 1969. Spurr was active in many professional associations, serving at various times as president, chairman, or other officer in the Society of American Foresters, Lake States Forest Tree Improvement Committee, and Organization for Tropical Studies while on the Michigan faculty.
In 1971 Spurr left the University of Michigan to become president of the University of Texas. He was fired from that position in 1974, but remained on the faculty there. Spurr died in 1990.
This collection contains correspondence and other papers relating to Spurr's professional activities while he was on the faculty of the University of Michigan. It also includes a small amount of material relating to his faculty activities. The collection is made up of four series: Correspondence, Organization for Tropical Studies, Ramparts Canyon Dam (Alaska) proposal, and Reprints.
Subjects:
Alaska.; Central America.; Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Forests and forestry--United States.; Organization for Tropical Studies.; Rampart Canyon Dam Project (Alaska); Spurr, Stephen Hopkins.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
Contributors:
Gruening, Ernest, 1887-1974.
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Association for Tropical Biology 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Australia 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Kenneth P. 1952-1960 (Box 1)
  - Doctoral theses--Readerships 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Ecological Society of America 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Fontanna, S. G. 1952-1959 (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Compact Commission 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Harvard Forest and University 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - International Union of Forest Research Organizations 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Lake States Forest Tree Improvement Committee and Conference 1956-1961, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan forestry 1953 (Box 1)
  - New Zealand 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - New Zealand--Fulbright 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Pauley, Scott S. 1952-1957 (Box 1)
  - Photogrammetry 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - Tropical forestry 1957 (Box 1)
  - Tropical studies committees--Other universities 1966 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Center for Tropical Studies 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - Ecology 1959 (Box 1)
    - Forest Properties Committee 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - Niehuss--Hatcher--Heyns 1960-1965 (Box 1)
    - Staff correspondence 1952-1961 (Box 1)
    - Students 1952-1962 (Box 1)
    - Tropical Studies Committee 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - University of Minnesota--Students 1952-1958 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1955-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Organization for Tropical Studies
  The Organization for Tropical Studies series (Boxes 2-3) documents Spurr's work in the founding and early development of the organization.
  - Correspondence 1963-1968, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Advisory committees 1968 (Box 2)
  - Application of University of Connecticut 1966 (Box 2)
  - British Honduras 1967 (Box 2)
  - Charter 1963-1967 (Box 2)
  - Committees and associate directorship appointment 1968 (Box 2)
  - Costa Rica 1967 (Box 2)
  - Courses 1964-1968 (Box 2)
  - Geography 1966 (Box 2)
  - Grant proposals 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Information summaries 1960s (Box 3)
  - International Education Act of 1966, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Marine Biology Committee 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Minutes 1963-1966 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation proposals 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Program 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Spencer, Jack 1968 (Box 3)
  - Staff reports--Tropical studies and maps 1962 (Box 3)
  - Summer meeting 1967 (Box 3)
  - Tropical biological programs and stations 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea, 5 folders (Box 3)
- Ramparts Canyon Dam (Alaska) proposal 1964-1966
  The Ramparts Canyon Dam (Alaska) proposal series (Boxes 3-4) includes correspondence and reports relating to a study by Spurr and others of the environmental impact of the proposed dam. The study was commissioned by the Natural Resources Council of America.
  - AAAS meeting, Berkeley December 1965 (Box 3)
  - Alaskans, Private individuals (Box 3)
  - Brewer, Michael (Box 3)
  - Brooks, Paul (Box 3)
  - Canada (Box 3)
  - Consultant staff (other than Brewer and Leopold) (Box 3)
  - Fitzgerald, Joseph H. (U.S. Dept. of Commerce) (Box 3)
  - Leopold, A. Starker (Box 3)
  - Natural Resources Council of America, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Nuclear power (Box 3)
  - Progress reports, Staff reports (Box 4)
  - Staff conference, Ann Arbor January 1965 (Box 4)
  - State of Alaska, University of Alaska (Box 4)
  - U.S. Congress (Box 4)
  - U.S. Dept. of Defense (Box 4)
  - U.S. Dept. of the Interior (Box 4)
  - U.S. Forest Service (Box 4)
  - U.S. industries (Alcoa, Bechtel, Westinghouse) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1964-1971, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Reprints
  - 1940-1970, 173 items (Box 4)
Related Material
Some records produced by Spurr in his administrative positions at the University of Michigan can be found in the records of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies and the University of Michigan Vice-President for Academic Affairs. The records of the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources contain little, if any, Spurr material.